okay
it is
may 19th 2022 and it's week three of the
textbook group
first cohort
we're in week three
discussing appendix a and b
and
there are some notes in
the sections of the book in the chapters
there are also some ideas and questions
that people have raised
so we'll
go to the questions and then start with
the most upvoted so feel free to add
more upvotes
if you want to discuss it
like even in this
discussion and then hopefully
if people are available to take notes in
this section that will help add their
thoughts in
and also capture what the speakers are
saying
and then we'll look at the question and
then
try to come to different answers and
just add more information that people
can add
more structure to later
okay the first question says appendix a
is described as a mathematical
background
so
maybe question one
for the authors or for you what is the
process of determining what is figuring
ground for the formalisms
of active
what other math concepts and formalisms
are important for learning and applying
active inference
and then three what are some resources
and approaches
for
learning math that help us learn what
isn't what is useful for active
inference
anyone can raise their hand or we can
just start to add some annotations here
like
what should be included in the primary
regime of attention with a
reading of a book either linearly like
some books are
or in a maybe moving around the sections
so what should be in the chapters
[Music]
what should be in the appendix what is
not in the appendix
what did people expect would be in the
chapter in the appendix not covered
yeah jessica and then anyone else
um yeah i was wondering
about the multiplication of the matrices
that we covered yesterday um which
equations and
have
the multiplication of the matrices
like a couple of examples just so i can
like
play around with them
like in the actual like active inference
equations
does anyone um know one
this is referencing
the way that the appendix a is starting
with linear algebra
and then
introducing this operation of
um multiplying two matrices or
to get a product
if someone can find
like an equation from the tr that we've
already seen or some other equation
while i'm typing up that question that
would be helpful
could anyone
just describe what they
thought
the intention was of
starting with linear algebra and using
8.1 is the first equation of the
appendix or we'll return to just the
more
general questions
yeah um
i mean linear algebra is kind of the
most
discreet
um
i don't want to say fundamental but like
uh practical and comprehensive way of
kind of
working with a large space of data i
guess um together
and computing on it so
it's kind of the basis for
the discrete
parts
and maybe easier than the non-discrete
good reason to start
i guess if the question was
where is a linear algebra used in the
active inference
math
when you go to
appendix b
then
the equations of active inference
and these are all expressed in terms of
large vector spaces of
variables so probability distributions
and so for example on page 245 you've
got this dot notation which is the
expectation
of a value
so that that
goes directly back to that first section
of appendix a is what does that mean in
terms of how do you take an expectation
of a large
vector of things how do you express that
compactly
thanks um could you
unpack uh we looked at the dot notation
a little bit
in uh yesterday
and
they were mentioning how well i think it
was actually one of the questions too
let's just see if someone asked this
okay
they say the dot operator
in a3
the dot operator is equivalent to
standard matrix multiplication
where the first matrix has been
transposed
so
what is the relationship with
expectation
when we're talking like what are where
how does expectation this is for anyone
how does expectation relate to
linear algebra
yeah expectation is the probability
of a value
the average probability of some value so
you're going to take all the possible
values
and you're going to multiply them by the
probability of that
value
and then divide by the sum of the you
know well probability normal is to one
so that will be the expectation so if
you have a whole array or a vector of
you know in your distribution
you can express that all in compact
notation by saying with this simple way
of saying we're going to take every one
of these terms and we're going to
multiply it by the probability of that
term
and
the probability sum to 1 so then that
will be your your average
overall
awesome thanks for that answer
um
[Music]
okay thanks for that awesome answer does
anyone have any other
thoughts on just this first question
and then we'll continue so
what
is figuring ground
we're learning active inference in the
chapters that's why the chapters are
there
the appendix is there to somehow
lightly supplement that
like they describe it as
an introduction or a refresher to the
basic basic mathematical techniques
and linear algebra
is the first section
a2
that is discussing a lot of important
things like derivatives and
probabilities
taylor series variational calculus and
stochastic dynamics are going to come in
in the coming chapters
but the linear algebra is is a important
for the upcoming chapters
okay
so
this question asked in a3
they say the dot operator is equivalent
to standard matrix multiplication where
the first matrix has been transposed
which is flipped like it's the operation
in google sheets or excel right click
paste transpose
they say that in the case of column
matrices
this is equivalent to the dot product
so the dot operator here is like a
generalization of the vector dot
operator the sum of the products of the
corresponding entries of the two
sequences of numbers
so the questions here were what
is interpretation implication or use of
the dot product of vectors
and then what is an interpretation
implication or use of a more generalized
dot product and it looks like there's a
awesome answer
what would be a situation
where
if anyone can think of one like
the dot product would be applied
like you know
we're just we're trying to do this in
this situation
this is the operation that we needed
we wanted to compute matrix a on
something
of something
we used b dot c
um
let's continue eric's
uh description
from probability like if you have
expectation probability
and you wanted to
kind of see the error or
uh
whatever the difference i guess uh
between observation and
and the expectation
then a dot product would give you
that answer
or
i think it's a probability density of it
what are some ways to compute
differences
like you can if there are scalars you
can subtract
like five minus three or something
then it was mentioned of cosine
similarity
does anyone think of or or imagine like
another way that you could compute the
difference between two different
like kinds of
features of different dimensions
like another example is divergence
because that's like measuring the
differences between these two
distributions and there's different
divergences the kl is one of them
what uh what other things are in this
space that might be just
tractable
possible distance measures
well
i mean these are these are the same
dimensionality
in all these cases but
another
very popular one is the sum square
difference
sum squared error
and then um
you can have absolute different value
difference
so these are called different um norms
i think that's what i work
yes
there's also the ginny index
the jacquard index
um
euclidean distances like samples of
sample distances
so
um
did anyone
talk about l0 l1 and l2 etc norms while
i'm adding some links
uh if i have the right
numbers here l to norm would be the
square root of the sum of squares l one
norm would be
the
um
average of the absolute absolute value
differences
and l zero i don't know what that is uh
well i don't think that's a difference
is it it's like a presence absence
okay
just
so it's like a
that kind of encoding is used in a lot
of different
algorithms
and then the l2 norm
is the sum of squares
so the l2 norm is what is used like in a
least squares regression
classical statistics
t-test anova
that's a lot driven by the l2
norm
and all of that is like
in the genre of what the a3 notation is
describing
and they're but depending on what the b
and the c are and what the a is etcetera
there's just the dimensions of
everything and other operations that are
happening before after it
later on they mentioned the quadratic
which is the l2 norm so that's where you
have
the you know the same term is multiplied
by itself or if you have cross terms
then you get the covariance
and that's going to be used
later with the laplace approximation and
other approximation techniques
any other comments on a3
or dot product
or just like this like kind of linear
algebra
topic
linear algebra the
basics the trace and the determinant
which are probably less important than
the dot product but still come into play
the derivatives
how things change with respect to each
other
possibly time possibly some other
surface
and then probabilities
so does anyone have any other comments
or thoughts on that whole section like
anything that they read or like had
uncertainty around up to equation a22
great that no one has uncertainty around
any of the equations up to a22
yeah i mean
obviously there is a lot to like learn
and to understand and we're not going to
it's just i don't know people who want
to think about that like what are we
learning in appendix a
why is appendix a there
that hopefully we can start to
understand some of this in math learning
group
with the people who want to be really
engaged with the math
questioning
and process
and then
and also connecting it to computer
science into the applications like has
been happening
and then hopefully everyone can can
benefit from this like finding the
resources and stuff
because the relationships between the
terms relationships amongst the terms
are
driven by formalisms
like the way that preferences and
expectations are framed in active
inference
is related to equations
not
only a conceptual linkage
okay
maybe here we can just write math
learning group
and copy this to the resources
okay
so
what kinds of examples
do you think would be useful for
learning the equations and concepts in
appendix a
if the equations felt too general
and not applying to anything in
particular
what
example or scenario
or like
would have made sense or
you felt would have made that clearer
like we're running a business and first
this person wants to do this
and then this person wants to do that or
what example or what would somebody have
expected to have found or wanted to have
found
that would have made it clear
examples or other exercises
or a format this is kind of like a math
lecture
it's kind of directional versus like
what other things could happen where you
would feel like you were understanding
and learning this and engaging with it
jess thanks brock
i was kind of reminded of a video that
carl
um a presentation
um
where he
like in real time demonstrates
uh and helps you
work through like a pattern of red like
it's like three dots sort of that are
moving around red green and this pattern
and so
um
understanding
like uh just a simple visual example um
of how active inference
would work
um
[Music]
that doesn't
you know um require the formalism to
just you know uh the surface level kind
of pattern recognized
that would be like ideal maybe of then
bringing in the math for this part and
that part and
some scaffolding you know um but
yeah i'm not i'm not sure the appendix
i'm not sure it was meant to be bread
and
i'm not sure there's a great way to read
one order or another there like
because you kind of need it but you kind
of
yeah
a lot too right so
great point and uh like
the organizing team for the textbook
group which
was open to everybody who wanted to join
the edu and the comms weekly meetings so
for future cohorts people could totally
be involved with planning it
communicating it
doing anything for future cohorts
as a co-organizer or other role
but we talked a lot about the reading
order
would it make sense to
read them
in
without
appendix or putting the appendix last
or somewhere else
um
one was short and hopefully the one week
of regime of attention on appendix a and
b is like
we're just
skimming it in a week
we're not
getting a phd in math
we're not generating these equations on
a blank piece of paper
we're just like seeing the forms
that will be used and then some of the
key areas
in the order that the authors thought
that those background topics were
important so like for appendix a
linear algebra which is what we talked
the most about because it's going to
come into play
most quickly
especially with these notions of like
expectation and differences
which is going to come into play
with everything that's going to happen
taylor series
variational calculus and stochastic
dynamics
we talked less about
they happened in a later order within
the appendix
but hopefully there will still be many
questions on them
because they're probably also areas with
a lot to learn and to clarify
and also appendix a is like not the
final
resource of it diffusing into us
like something that was really important
came up in the math learning group
is
there's not like a glossary of variables
or table of variables so that's
something we can work on with notation
is connecting the variables
to natural language ontology terms
and then also
things like this
what do we even look up
or a symbol
or what does it mean when there's a
double arrow there's a lot of things
that
like a lot of dots that could be
connected
if people ask them
and then we can probably get a response
like what was the double arrow in a3
what does it mean anything that they're
offset
or what is what are the parts of this
shape that are mattering
for the background of learning active
inference
anyone can ask like any question if it's
coming to mind as an uncertainty
then writing it down just anywhere is
really helpful
because then
on the first pass through learning or a
primary branch of learning we can just
go okay here's what a1 shows
and then have that in a way that reduces
uncertainty more rapidly than
how any of us would just give an ad hoc
explanation
yeah one thing that i i always find
useful in thinking about matrix you know
linear algebra matrices is to write out
pictures of the matrices in their
dimensions because often the notation
you've got these eyes and j's and k's
and stuff going around but you don't
know how that maps out into the actual
elements of the matrix so
those illustrations are always helpful
that are
you know could be added into this this
book they're in a few places but not
that much
there you go those things like that and
yeah yeah and also like connecting the
programming experience that people might
have even in no code tools like
excel google sheet like you have rows
and columns
ones have numbers and ones have letters
but they can be other things
and then
anyone who has used something like
python or r
or even just doing some statistical
calculations like if you put two lists
of numbers into the t-test
that would be vector versus vector
something and then you would address the
fifth element of the list
and then if it was in excel you would
need to address two numbers
to say where you were in the matrix and
then the tensor is just any number of
more than
three dimensions
which is sometimes like it's like oh but
how spatially are we going to see it but
then we're familiar with working with
spreadsheets and data sets
that are
larger than two by two or larger than
two dimensions
so
like you could and and that will come
into play a lot and the numbers can be
representing probabilities or be used
for probabilities
i also daniel share in the chat shared a
link to a python notebook that has
uh there's a link and it shows kind of
the operations on matrices and kind of
you know you can see both the
the mathematical yeah there you go and
so you can see the actual matrix and you
can actually run code too there so that
particular so awesome
so i pasted the link in here and then
we'll just
we'll we can fill out the
rest of the row
but then
someone could be looking for a guide on
matrix
or programming and matrix or something
before this state
so then each person if they find it and
add it here will have a lot
to share and learn
okay does anybody want to like if they
were the one who asked it this question
i think it's probably referring to long
equations that that probably none of us
are ready to give answers to at this
point
unless somebody wants to
contextualize this question
okay i'm hoping a read of chapter four
will elucidate when the time comes just
exploring the formal foundations here
okay
does anyone have a favorite or
recommended textbook that it contains
the kl divergence
and dirichlet distribution in the index
this is for the math learning group okay
maybe we could tag some questions too
and so then we can know which ones that
they can look at
um wikipedia is good
the kl divergence is approachable the
dirichlet is tougher
the links take you to definitions that
enable you to put the pieces together
okay
any comments on kl
and dear schley
from someone who is familiar otherwise
like it sounds very technical and we
don't need to go into it right now
what is up with dividing by sigma
in a 31.
also
detail
but we'll just see if there's any
questions that are not going to be
specific details because math is very
hard to
it like
understands sometimes on the fly
and there's definitely a space for the
interactive discussions around math
that are unrecorded
which are important
however this is a little bit of a
different format
so
which is how i'm hopefully interpreting
people's
activity
rather than their disengagements because
they are here and hopefully having
scanned these
chapters
anyone can raise their hand at any time
or
add questions or upload things
mean field
mode
equation 9 equation 16
probability resource
statistical question
appendix b just to see if there is any
also seem like all details
so we have 23 minutes what does anybody
want to
ask
now
or is there some
question
here like the most upvoted one or some
other one that's far less
challenging
that they would like to address for the
next 20 minutes
did anyone read appendix a or b visually
did you just ask if anyone read it
yes what would anyone like to share
about reading it
i totally read it um with
a highlighter and
made several notes in the margin in my
physical book
um it was challenging a lot of the
notation i feel like
um
is
like crazy
like like um i mean
even just in appendix b like the very is
was it the very first thing like are
they using o
for observations are they using o for
outcomes like i was totally unclear on
that um completely
so like state inference markov decision
processes like
um the states that influence outcomes oh
right
like literally that's what it says on
the top of page 244.
so it says that the variable o is an
outcome
is an outcome and observation are those
the same thing are they interchangeable
like
i've always thought oh was observations
um that i put that question in there
in a picture
it's already there um
and and then the the the question right
before it like this is a really a really
tricky section right so
there's two the two questions that are
in appendix b that are together it says
the likelihood of observations given a
policy is not straightforward to compute
this is because pomdp problem is
structured so that policies pi
influence trajectories indicated by
tilda of states s that influence
outcomes o without a direct influence of
policies on outcomes
the problem then involves a sum over
trajectories of states to marginalize
these out and find a marginal likelihood
of observations given policies like what
does that these even refer to if you
look in the questions in appendix b like
they're there in the questions already
listed so i mean
i felt like it was very obscure and not
super clear and also like the notation
gets crazy
um and i'm like really a stickler for
like defining every single variable and
symbol in an equation to understand the
math so that i can actually read it in
english so i was a little bit lost
totally agree
thanks for sharing it
eric just with respect to that
particular question
um
i think that these refers to the
trajectories of states and you can see
that because the sum is over the tilde s
so the tilde s is the trajectories of
states
so you sum over all the trajectories of
states to try to figure out well what
are we going to get
if we apply a given policy
that's my intuition about that
and i suspect also that observations are
outcomes they're sensory outcomes
they're the outcome of a generative
model
or a generative process but they're the
outcome
that is observed
but
how many how many dots we need to
actually unpack and connect for
unsighted
grammatically vague sentences
right like so thank you my uncertainty
has been reduced substantially just by
like
figuring that out but like i felt like
that the whole time i was reading the
appendix is like what is even going on
here
yeah so
in you know
yes sir the way i view it is like
exercising
you're not going to run a marathon the
first time you you set out but you know
the more you you stretch and warm up
and that's kind of i think that's how i
kind of view this uh going through the
appendix is kind of refreshing on what
you used to know about math or at least
for me
and so that's like stretching and doing
a little bit of exercise the last week
and then every time you go through it
every time you see the notation you've
slept on it some more
it becomes more more familiar and so you
can start to put together bigger bigger
chunks some vaguely you can map to the
notation
and the math other ones it's still going
to be dangling but that's okay because
there's fewer dangling things that
you're groping with at any
given moment so i think it's great to go
through these dependencies and see it
all through one pass and all right so i
didn't run a marathon but that's okay i
ran two miles that's pretty good for
first start
thanks eric
another like metaphor is just like oh
yes please
jakub
yeah i was just i was just gonna uh
comment on what uh blue said
uh with the kind of
some
um confusion about the notation because
uh
i asked the question about the
the marginalizing of states but then i
was also confused about the o notation
because
um
in the in equation b b.1 it kind of
it it seems that it's a trajectory over
outcomes but then there's also an o
without a tilde on it
so does that mean that it's an outcome
at a particular point in time but then
there's also
a bold o
which
implies that it's kind of a vector but
if it's a trajectory of outcomes that's
also that also seems to be a vec like a
trajectory
for me implies some kind of vector form
uh because it's a sequence of outcomes
given a policy but then
what does that
bold o uh
mean if not trajectories over outcomes
so
just to kind of
add to the uh confusion i
guess thanks jacob i'm glad like we're
groking we're on the same page you and i
for sure
um
it would be awesome for description or
any notes
what is the reading or a reading in
language
the this of this conditioned on that
is this over that
of these two things the first thing is
this the second one is that
an example of that is in this situation
here's the script
here's the graphical abstract here's the
paper
here's the person you could ask
which one of these do you think is going
to be interesting
okay so mike asked and i'll copy this in
for those who have read the entire book
did you find the appendices useful as
you went along through the chapters
uh ali
uh yeah i also think that uh if these
the materials in these two appendices
were to be integrated in uh
in the linear
narrative of the whole book
it would be much more useful than
separating out as
i mean separate appendices because
as as we see i i mean that's my own
experience well reading the chapters
independently and in isolation of the
narrative it doesn't give me a sense of
their uh concrete applications and
i don't know how to use them and how to
use these uh for
all of these equations and
everything becomes much more fuzzy
i hope this is not controversial that
linear reading of the appendix as
something that you look through
is extremely confusing or extremely
imprecise because there's many symbols
introduced
that might have been introduced earlier
like o is probably
discussed earlier
but then it's
briefly just sort of mentioned and then
there's a lot of symbology that's not
mentioned what it is
so it's hard to read the appendix
without prior knowledge
yet ostensibly appendix a
is the introduction refresher
so is this the introduction
offering
they hope so they expect and prefer
perhaps the appendix to go some way
towards remedying
it
being the maths required to understand
this not complicated
basis
the multidisciplinary basis means it is
often difficult to find resources that
bring together the necessary
prerequisites
they're going some way
so this is like one kind of plank out
there from their point of view from the
chapters
this is stuff like i also kind of agree
like on what what ordering these are
really interesting questions
so then what is the next
connector
that picks up here with this artifact
because um like someone mentioned how um
you
more it's mentioned you could basically
do a whole course on deep learning to
apply most of the matrix operations
and whole courses on like the math of
them
so they can't go into all this detail
they can't spend one hour
or like multiple coda pages on just what
this means
so there has to be some kind of
compromise but then there's not going to
be one specific perfect compromise
with especially with like length and
audience considered
so i think like um i mean i undertook
like a very detailed linear reading of
of the book because that's just kind of
how i am of the appendixes at least but
i think um for many people that like
i mean i've been there before like where
you're staring at math equations like
this is gibberish but like
so just to read the text you know and
like to read it and go through it it's
helpful to know that it's there so if
nothing else at least like you can be
reading the book and then be like oh i
remember kind of reading about you know
taylor series expansion in the appendix
and so then you can just go back and
just having access to it or the the
refresh recall access um even though it
is confusing i agree to try to a linear
read of the appendix it's um
i think
skimming over it or deeply reading it
and then being able to refer back to it
is useful
thanks blue
um so
in
next week
we're going next two weeks so the pace
of one section per week
might be like whatever it was for you
however much time you put in et cetera
the coming chapters are going to be very
different
because one didn't have any formalisms
or figures really
just the kind of overview figures
but we're gonna have two weeks for two
so
no need to rush it read a couple pages
and then just go back to the beginning
and just restart the same pages like
that's like the multiple coats of paint
in a mural
like the low road to active inference
that's where they're gonna pick up in
that high road low road
um
dialectic that we talked about last time
let's just see like what figures what
equations might happen okay a lot of
terms
that
um hopefully are in
the ontology already like you can use
the at
symbol
hopefully to call most of them
but if something's not there we can add
it to like supplemental or entailed
okay
so what figures
and eq figures and equations what we
might see
here's a box
2.1
about probability
here's an equation
that's
the bayesian
kernel
and it's going to be
talking about this example of a frog and
an apple
and jumping or not jumping
and that example is gonna play
our current role but then some
likelihoods are shown
in a specific example of like frogs and
jumping or not and apples
there's a work through example of
exact bayesian inference
here's a table on statistical
distributions
it would be really interesting like to
hear what support and surprise mean
and why what are these are these all the
distributions are there other ones or
like why these ones or why are they
useful
where have they been used what does it
even mean
here's where the kl divergence
is introduced
and then
some more analysis from a surprise
perspective bayesian surprise
with the kl divergence
there's the box on expectations which is
also what we talked about a little bit
today and i was like really interesting
to connect it to the matrices
a figure
of the
generative process in the generative
model
is the caption
a figure
both perception and action minimize
discrepancy between model and world
variational free energy
variational free energy as an upper
bound on negative log evidence
a figure but with equations in it
very common format
bigger
complementary roles of perception and
action in the minimization of
variational free energy
big active theme and like something a
kind of a common fristenism
like perception action being in the same
game
or being in the same service of the same
objective function
planning
but no specific equations but probably
citations
just introducing expected free energy
which jacob and and others can probably
go into a lot more detail on
expected free energy
about a future where the outcomes
haven't happened
expected free energy figure with
equations
the end of the low road
introducing the two
key terms variational free energy
expected free energy
summary
what does anybody like want to like add
or what was something cool or whether
they read it already or not
what does anyone i'll eat yes please
uh well i've noticed the dispersion of
some
sidebar boxes like box 2.1 or
in this chapter
i don't know the distinction between
the purpose of these boxes and
i mean
what's the function of these boxes uh as
compared to
what we see in the appendices
because presumably
these boxes cover the concepts that
could be skipped over if one is familiar
with
these mathematical concepts so
do you have any idea
about the reason
behind this decision i mean
uh
covering some basic concepts basic
mathematical concepts in these
sidebar boxes and some others in the
appendices
that's a great question
a box could reflect like
okay expectations got it or like okay
some product rule all right
but it's kind of like you might want to
read that or is this introductory
highlighting it
this is the 101 on probability
or is it saying this is a total
skippable unit if you want to learn
about how the lizard does it
here's where you look
it can it can sometimes mean both and
like
the the format of the book is also
relatively
austere though in a concise tone
um
like
it's in black and white
which especially in some later sections
makes some visualizations
where it's like
it's hard to understand like where like
what curves are doing what
it's a black and white image so what is
there to see with the color i mean or
but
it also might predispose towards more
simple or
visually accessible
material
so what is going to be accessible
and the order so those are all really
important questions
so we can just take notes on it you know
in the weeks that we're going to
continue to do this because we only have
limited live time
how about in the last like three minutes
what does anybody think about the
opening
quotations
or specifically this quotation
my thinking is first and last and always
for the sake of my doing william james
you know i thought the guy was a
philosopher so i guess you just abused
me of that one
these would be really
nice areas to look into
for people who like the history part
um blue
and i and others are working on some
different kinds of ways to reference
papers and
just up cool paper
sensation perception
we have those terms we could just link
the paper somewhere
so if anyone's like interested in that
kind of architectures
or
that kind of philosophy question
[Music]
those are
the literature right now is small enough
to know what has and hasn't been done in
a lot of areas
that are philosophical and applied and
technical
just from like a first principles what
does this seem to mean
uh that
shared that other group that that we're
kind of
both a part of daniel um
the liminal
dowel thing that's not really a dow i
don't know what it is but there's this
debate
for some reason that's going on there
about
you know different ways of knowing and
being and doing and a bunch of stuff uh
that is kind of
a mix of philosophy and linguistic
fallacies but um
like if
if thinking
is actually a physical process which i
think you know
i don't think anyone here is going to
argue against
then it is something necessarily that is
being done
and
so however i guess small you want to
draw that markov blanket up and then
however large whether that's your
physical body actions or
some extended thinking
it's
literally
what you're doing uh
they're
it's not just for the sake of your
actions but it's
they are your actions
like they're just others another set of
your actions
all right let me i'll offer a different
take on it
yeah awesome william william james was a
great visionary
and he foresaw
marx mark zuckerberg's meta metaverse
100 and
20 years ago or whatever and he said no
i don't want to live just inside my mind
inside the metaverse
i want to be out in the world interact
with real people and real things so he
was
a
meta or facebook skeptic
way before his time
okay thank you ali
yeah as brock mentioned uh i think it
relates to an epistemology
epistemological
um
i mean distinction between uh
propositional knowledge and uh how to
knowledge and i think uh this statement
by uh
this statement here uh tries to blur
this distinction blurs the line between
uh
propositional knowledge and know-how
knowledge because in especially in
analytical
uh school of philosophy uh
there's always been
a very um
uh
let's say um
not a heated debate but uh
there's a long-standing uh debate uh
about uh
about the distinction between these uh
two kinds of knowledge and whether uh
they're in fact uh they can be uh
distinguished from each other or not
thank you could you just unpack what are
the two kinds of knowledge again and
what are just
they referring to
sure
well
about propositional knowledge
well an example of propositional
knowledge is uh to know
uh the exact um
mechanisms of walking uh i mean
which muscles contract and uh which
i mean in what
angles uh the the uh
i mean the whole thing about the
uh biomechanics of walking the whole
knowledge about the biomechanics of
knowledge uh can constitute
this kind of propositional knowledge
and
it's totally different from knowing how
to walk
i mean
a three or four year old year old child
has a know-how knowledge of walking but
not necessarily
where he or she doesn't know
anything about the biomechanics of
walking so the biomechanics of walking
is the propositional knowledge
actually knowing how to walk constitutes
the know-how of
walking
so when people say things like
active inference is integrating
perception cognition and action
maybe it is rethinking
some of these long-held mental
frameworks for distinguishing or
operating differently on action and
perception
like one
fascinating recent example from me was
and working with eric
was
in the area of ant pheromone modeling
without going into too many details
people often modeled preference as a
function of the absolute amount
of pheromone on trails
because that's what the exponential like
decay is on that's what can be
manipulated
rather than
the perceived intensity
which might have a different scaling
relationship so it's like a dim room you
can detect a small change bright room
you can't detect a small change
so that kind of psychophysics
of perception
gets ignored
implicitly
because of calls for measurability
because the cognitive can't be measured
directly
even if you potentially had a
electrical measurement or something like
that happening
then these are awesome questions can you
think without acting or is thinking in
action
this
active paper
which was on a live stream so we can
provide the link to
it models like perception and action in
the sort of like
kernel level
just the autonomous sensing sentient bot
level
and then attention and metacognition are
both
related as actions
to the lower level
which is like why the paper
is
relating computational
phenomenology with mental action
again just to have like a look at the
kinds of models that
can happen
and then
now does making any model fitting any
data well enough and saying well we
modeled it as action
so is thinking an action
will that model that says yeah it's
consistent with that will that ever
constitute positive evidence for saying
thinking is action
or why even
say that or what does it mean to say it
and then here's a funny meme
[Music]
here's the generative model
and the generative um the partially
observable markov decision process
here's carl fristen
jessica and then anyone else
ah yes um
i guess it's like a beginning
understanding of this it's like
i tend to think that um
there's like a bias towards action in
active inference i think like the first
chapter saying like
you know even if you wanna like stand so
like perceive you have to do some kind
of action in order to um gain the
information
and and this like you know quote it's
basically saying like okay
even though
the whole field is trying to understand
cognition
it's like
what we decide to do and the thinking
that we go through in order to determine
our policy is to determine our actions
and then it sort of like feed into um
the thinking itself so maybe that's why
there's like the bias to action
and
because like our actions is what it's
going to be allowing the thinking
but
um
yeah like when we update our models or
like you know trying to come up with
like the policies that we're going to be
doing like we have to be processing
things
so you know the thinking is in like
as a service to action and
that's sort of like what i was thinking
i don't know it's a little bit like you
know with the chicken and the egg but
and
you know i kind of tend to think of it
it's like yes like we have to act in
order to understand
but and like the understanding which
will be coming from the thinking is what
determines our next action
and
yeah that's kind of what i think
matthew thanks jessica
yeah i mean it kind of seems to me like
we're stuck in a little bit of a
linguistic godelian loop of some sort
because you know thinking
is you know essentially a verb and verbs
tend to imply
in like linguistic immersion term
actions
and so we have to then pop outside of
that and try to consider with our
internal medical processes
how to disentangle these concepts but i
see no reason to think
that
to think ironically that
internal mental states aren't also
conscious parameterizations of processes
in the brain and our ability to grasp
control of that to some extent and so it
seems very strange to me to try to
separate those linguistically
from our current vantage point even
though i understand why historically
working only with language it might have
made sense
so
those kind of quotes like james is
strike me as somewhat
antiquated or just you know operating on
dichotomies that don't seem to make
sense given that we've unpacked these
processes to the degree we have
thank you matthew very
deep points
like you mentioned thinking as a verb
implies action
and then just to kind of
complete that
thought is like the word
for the noun form of this one
so then what does that imply
and then also like
jessica mentioned
to some extent that like we can only
express processes through their
discretization of you know via symbols
right
um
the idea that like there's this process
uh there's a flow there's something that
can't necessarily be separated um
obviously from the rest of the flows
around it but to reference it uh to
point to it to describe it communicate
it to another agent
we have to uh nounize it
kind of like
which is the opposite of verbalizing so
to speak
wow thank you matthew
um
again these are yes eric
sorry i didn't have anything i didn't do
okay the hand was yeah so
um
carl firsten had a influential
uh
paper
long paper
the
free energy principle for a particular
physics so that was in 2019 so it's been
several years since then and like
particular
allegedly slash
accidentally or intentionally is a pun
so it can mean specific
like a physics for the specific systems
that we're modeling
or it could be specific like this is a
specific approach
another interpretation is like it's for
particulate entities
when we define thing
and the partition
which is going to co-instantiate like
the generative model and the generative
process and then the markov blanket or
the interface that's separating them
that is
separating the figure from ground it's
separating like the entity from the
niche
it's separating what from what
what what can it represent the
separation of something from
all possible separations
some separations
and then
matthew you mentioned like yeah
verbalizing speech
but it feels like we're speaking
[Music]
maths sometimes
yet verbalization is a process
especially um dialogue yes matthew
could i ask a question that brings in a
little bit of content from the other
chapters of the book is that
yeah sure
i'm just kind of curious because when
you're talking about those um you're
talking about the markov blankets
and integrating it into this idea of how
we draw boundaries i'm kind of curious
is it fair to say
that to the extent we've drawn our
boundaries and do see
a reduction of free energy in this
system it reinforces the idea that
there's something
to that
boundary structure as an entity in the
world that there's a reality to that is
that a fair interpretation
i think many people would have a lot to
say and add this touches on like the
question of reification of scientific
models
and
the ability for an identified
statistical model
to be like transcending itself
and used in a realist way
like ontologically real about true
joints of the world
and um
i'm going to go to live stream table
and find several of the
of those who explained their research on
this topic
but even short return to claim it's real
like is it just
does that ability like once we've drawn
a boundary um using these markov
blankets uh and we do see that
it seems to be let's say using
information to um
self-evidence
do we think that that's i mean it seems
like the the the
this
you know this paradigm of thought is
predicated on the idea that um to the
extent that that occurs and reduces free
energy it shouldn't track or further
attract attention at the very least for
examination or investigation
yes so great questions jakob do you have
something to add on that or or is it a
slightly different area
i guess i guess it's kind of related um
to the to the mark of blanket discussion
um
i
know this
this may be completely wrong but it
seems to me like with
um
that this
kind of discretization of the markov
blankets forces us to
a specific kind of discrete thinking
but i feel like that
just this model of a of a markov blanket
i think of it as a kind of classical
model but
i presume that the reality is more
something like a schroedinger
markov blanket where
it's not we can't really draw boundaries
between
thinking and
observing a generative process
uh in the same way that we can't think
of
say electrons as balls bouncing off each
other but
they're not really we can think of them
as classical particles and that will
help us
um to an extent
but
then we can also observe
um the process of thinking so thinking
is also kind of
entangled with the generative process
so there's
so even though the markov blanket is a
useful formalism i think
that there will be
that there are definitely certain
scenarios that
um
in which
it's more like a probabilistic well it's
already probabilistic but
in the sense that
the
entity that's performing inference
also
in its own inference
um loop
um performs inference on itself
and therefore
thinking is at the same time an action
but at the same time it's
part of the generative process
okay another
angle on this
thanks jacob is what dean
d often talks about with like active
inference as a framework or a filter and
these are just sort of like you know
different distinctions that might be
transiently useful in some axis like
fitting something to a framework
it's kind of the procrustes bed stretch
it out so that this perception
and then active as a filter is was
reminding me of what matthew was saying
like going out and discovering
divergences from expectation of there
not being metabolic activity on a planet
and then there is some statistical
deviation
and so like in the classical statistical
framework that might be like it's a one
sigma difference
in the bayesian
framework well there's a bayes factor of
two and
here for this
evidence
and there's other ways to like talk
about
detection of novel entities that might
be part of like a reification process
of the
extended cognition of the modelers
and then like one philosophical angle on
that and then also anyone who who um
wants to then ali is um this book by
helen longino
which
talks about methodological pluralism
and about how there can be like
disciplinary rigor
and the ways in which often unstated
like social priors can
be
the substance of what becomes
understood to be science
as like a complex phenomena
um ali and then
brock adding to what jacob said um
i i think the
the concept of marco blanket emanates
from the plutonian
way of thinking uh
specifically the
hylomorphism uh school of thought uh as
um
as opposed to hylozoism uh well the
distinction between hydromorphism and
hydrozoism is that uh well in
hilomorphism
everything is disconnected every concept
is disconnected
and
with every other concept and so there's
a discontinuity a metaphysical
discontinuity uh between the concepts uh
but um
in hilozoism uh the philosophers uh
advocating this uh
school of thought uh
well they claimed that hylomorphism
fails at uh answering uh the question of
what it is adequately and so and they
even rephrased the the question and they
claim that the right question to ask is
not what it is
it's what it can do
so that's basically the distinction
between hylomorphism and hylosoism
but i think
the markov blanket
is a way of
formalizing this
hylomorphic
way of thinking
at least that's my opinion
thanks a lot for that ollie eric
sorry i'm not hearing eric you can
others hear eric
maybe i need to reload
come here
okay i'm gonna reload
[Music]
can you hear me yeah now i can hear blue
okay okay you're still not hearing eric
though
no sorry
yeah i just did like a small disrupt
um
okay
i'm gonna
okay wait eric try again okay how about
now yeah now it's now i can see you in
here again okay
how about everyone else
who's the audience
okay wow
disrupt in the um on the high-level
field
it's happened before
um
i would i just throw in my two cents
about um
my interpretation of a markup blanket
it's about
trying to make um
to
perform simplifications that make
computation tractable
um if you have everything interacting
with everything else then we can't do
computing on that so we um
we apply
compartmentalization and build objects
and interfaces for how the objects
interact with one another
um
and
those become tractable that's what um
you know
what a bayes net does is it says what
are independent and what are dependent
you know variables on each other
and um that works well when those
abstractions the objects and relations
the nouns and verbs
are a good fit to how the world actually
operates so that is a driver for
learning or building representations
that will use these markov blankets in
and put the compartments where they
actually are faithful to the way to the
compartmentalization
that we can abstract over the way the
world parts of the world operate so
things that are distant that separate
uh that interact only weekly we try to
maybe factor those out pretend they
don't interact at all or use some other
intermediate variables to to represent
the interaction in order to simplify
things so we can do computation so
that's that's how i think marco blankets
and we'll see if the math tells us that
later on when we get to it
awesome brock
ethan lee
okay i'm like not hearing brock
unfortunately do you
yes we all hear brock brook is reloading
i think now again okay
yeah gather does this sometimes
but
i don't know if it's if it's because we
have 15 people
yeah but it's yeah like matthew said i
don't see i don't hear him it's just
like there's different drop-offs
um
i can i can hear you but i still think
daniel can't hear you daniel you can't
wait now you're back
go for it okay continue
interesting can you hear me yeah oh okay
um
yeah no this is this is just this
ongoing thing that i don't know we just
keep
keeps coming up about yeah well okay
maybe they exist maybe they don't mark
up blankets really but like
how would they form
in any
um
like how how would they form and evolve
and collapse and
presumably
there is some point in
in that process this like evolution part
where
uh the markov blanket is
extremely poorly defined
uh
like relative to the system
right and that's basically
these
sort of under explored areas it was was
also in relation to matthew's question
also about um
the free energy minimization thing where
there's systems like non-equilibrium
systems basically where
um
still something interesting worth you
know
worthy of study is happening
but
perhaps
is not um
free energy minimizing
um at that
in that state
thanks for sharing it just a few
thoughts
like um
[Music]
just because so let's just say some sort
of
mesoscale or global as that's called but
that doesn't mean about the whole world
but some sort of global free energy
minimization in the joint model is
achieved like in a conversation
that isn't the same thing as the local
disconnected free energy minimization
otherwise fitting
high parameter models optimally would be
simply reducing to fitting single
dimensional models
alone if we could just do the linear
optimization on the standalone variables
then why would we ever need the larger
dimensional methods
and then
um
like think of this textbook
maybe with where things could be in the
coming years
the one the the the markov membrane
is like the linear algebra
and then jakob mentioned that this is
classical model
it is kind of classical in a sense
in the the timeless classic sense
so
the one layer marco blanket
when thinking about like the rise and
fall of
civilization is not
the end all that's like i think
maybe analogous to
a linear regression y equals mx plus b
and then you have like the height all
these 100 years of development on the
linear regression
model
and all these techniques and
applications and pipelines
so
the mark i'll blanket one layer
potentially over interpreting it as
already presenting with strengths or
weaknesses
in certain situations
when not being just like empirically
demonstrated
in the general case
we'll see what could be said and when
matthew
yeah um along those lines i was kind of
curious i've seen that there's been a
decent amount of work on the sort of
hierarchical or fractal composition of
these models um i'm curious if
that implies that there's a fractality
to the boundary by default or if they're
like is there any specific work on
sort of hierarchical composition of the
boundaries of that so-called membrane as
you said
with better annotation we could have
better answers because
there's many papers that we've discussed
in a guest stream or a paper and there's
also like many other papers obviously
that
that we don't have that kind of
annotations of
um
because
it's quite common to see nested
models
in the context of
nesting of cognitive processes like in
that sanfed smith paper which was i
think number 25
that was about cognition as mental
action
so that was nested and the nesting and
was interpreted as cognitive actions and
counterfactuals
basically and then sometimes nesting is
used to refer to actual like well
the state is inside of the country and
then the region is inside of the state
like it's it's implied
that the map is mapping on to the
territory
maybe even spatially the cell is inside
of the tissue
and that's like answering schrodinger's
question
everything happening with the planetary
scale analyses
cellular level
um
[Music]
and then this is
hopefully what is uh spoken to with like
the composability of active inference
and sometimes that's frame in terms of
like the the lateral composability
of like how you could have three ants
interacting or 300 ants and then the the
nested composability
you could have the fifth and the seventh
and all those layers
with computational tradeoffs maybe with
no extra information to be gleaned
and then
learning the structure of the generative
model or just the structure of the
partition
more broadly and like what the variables
are and everything
that's the structured learning
challenge
and
cognition as structured learning
synergetics geometry of thought
is what fristen has
and others have raised
as like a total open area
because there's the parameter
fine-tuning
once you have the bayes graph
so then you're you're you're now inside
of the ability to like
to reify or not that model
you're just doing parameter optimization
you know we used two factors in this
linear regression and then we optimized
it with the l2 norm two is the best
number of factors
but that it couldn't be said at that
scale you could say in a two parameter
model this is the best parameters
with this norm
but then you couldn't pull back another
level
and so that's like
meta scientific and metabasian analyses
which they're going to talk about like
later
okay yeah i guess i'm also kind of
wondering if there are any uh examples
that come to mind of something like a
system that is structured such as
the clearest or simplest example that
comes to mind is like let's say that you
have a nation and a
state within that nation and there is a
port and there is an overlap of sort of
that port interface to an outside
structure that is shared by both the
national and overlapping national and
state interests and decision processes
um and so i'm kind of curious if there
are examples of demonstrating that kind
of composability of generative models
um or if that's something that's still
just new and open
those are awesome questions if people
know any
um
some areas to investigate like in the
phenomena that you're you know
overlapping interests informally
there would be like shared regimes of
attention
there's the question of synchrony
and that doesn't mean like um
synchronization
identically but generalized synchrony
then there's like coordination of
affordances
we're not going to do this because of
that so that's like
um
in an area that that jacob and others
have been working on is just describing
that situation
as an affordance on an affordance
or like e sub e like it it's not in the
textbook but you know if people are
staying this long then this is just kind
of some ways that some people are
thinking about it and these are the
areas where people can also do research
and learning with us
but like
affordance is on affordances
the safety could be on or off so then
there's like an affordance that modifies
another affordance and could those have
compositionality
just like some of these other
um
generalization
affordances for generalization basically
what are those
and then isn't it like discovering what
those are
just
really i think uh it's kind of also
related to that question of this
formation evolution collapse of markup
blankets is when
when
does the observation actions of one
system
map to the
to the preferences of another and vice
versa how does that
come into
being existence how does that start to
happen and how does it
unhappen
i don't
know
awesome question thank you and and
another like angle on that
let me just check um and then ali is
like this is a graph that we're going to
look at a ton and we will interpret what
all of it means
what is the o a s b
pi g etc
but
this is a bayesian graph like eric
mentioned and the edges are like
dependencies not causal influences in
the world but apparent potentially or
different interpretations
is this the only skeleton
no
this is the y equals mx plus b of
skeletons
and there's the the linear regression in
the first equation in the textbook of
the stats textbook and then there's all
these accessory tests
then there's like creation and
destruction
as applied
maybe there can just be a loop that's
not active inference just checking every
day if something's within an arbitrary
threshold
so there could be some
liminal or gray area
like an interface
i think steven salette mentioned it as
like a nail bed or something
like an interface between more
particulate and then less particulate
more more
field
versus the particle
ali
well as a little side note
there's a popular science book coming
out i think in june uh namely the
romance of reality by bob yazarian uh
which uh touches on uh the uh
uh the emergence of markup blankets uh
the dynamics of the emergence of markup
blankets and it
uh attacks um
attacks attacks it from
many different angles evolutionary angle
i mean from a cosmic even uh perspective
and uh it even goes for goes
as far as uh
well
considering the whole cosmos the whole
universe
uh as
um
let's say a kind of
meta
metamark of blankets uh so to speak and
uh well uh i think uh that
could be an interesting thought
uh put forward by bobby azarian in this
book all right thanks daniel
thanks um in fact he gave part one of
what was
uh intended and may still be like a
multiple part
discussion
but this was him giving that
presentation
so
we were in contact is definitely you
know it's an interesting view
and it's going to take all kinds of
research and and education and
communication
jessica
yes i mean i guess um
when i like first like joined the lab
like some of the sort of like um ideas
that helped me a little bit like to want
like to start even like
conceptualizing this um i mean in
addition to the filter that you
mentioned before daniel and like how
like
it could be like
more like porous or a lot like or more
hard and allow things in and out
but it was also um about like
it could be like i'm just grouping of
relationships and an interaction so like
the closer like a relationship like
different things art and
maybe that's more like on biological
systems i don't know like if
they're closely related
or they have like more interactions even
though they might be different but
like grouping it in those sense
and maybe that's relates to what eric
said and from the calculational part
and but that was sort of like you know
some of the things like when i started
connecting on markov blankets too
uh i started like okay if
you know
items or like different objects and
things like they're closely related
you can start like putting on like a
blanket around on
and maybe go so like with the idea of
wrapping things on
from some of the definitions but yeah
those are kind of like the kind of
visual ideas that i
you know started like helping me a
little bit uh and i still like don't
understand properly but those are the
things i was like okay so relationships
filters um like
kind of like connecting interactions and
between things
awesome thanks a lot for that like
interacting entities
so you could
have the edges representing some
interaction
like when people are fitting a linear
model interacting variables
so there's this whole
discussion topic of whether the
interactions are like the two ants
bumping into each other
whatever that means in the quote real
world
and then there's like the statistical
interaction
so
then defining certain variables in
statistical models so leaving that
debate behind us
and just talking about the statistical
models that we have bayesian graphs
some variables have edges between them
that could be either like designed to
there be there or not
or you could do some sort of like
thresholding approach and explore that
your thresholding parameter was
acceptable but like the more of a loose
interaction you allow
the the more challenge there is to fit
that statistical model
and you may not have enough data to fit
like the 10 variable by 10 variable with
all the interaction terms
which is like why would doing linear
modeling in
a health population example
they would like do model selection
on what their statistical power is
with that data set to resolve certain
kinds of effects and correlations and
like non-sphericities
and that is addressed a lot in the spm
textbook
and firstin's earlier like pre-active
work
but then you mentioned like
how to like be engaged with that process
of like the wrapping or the seeing the
clusters and knowing like where is there
going to be like maybe generative models
arising that are
consisting of other generative models or
other generative processes
and then like some things interact more
with others
statistically
in the model as by design or just as an
outcome of
whatever
so there's sparse connectivity amongst
the variables they're not like all by
all connected
and then that sparse connectivity
simplifies a lot of things that's also
related to like a lasso regression
and also to the
below l2 norms
and then a sparse model can be
factorized
and that is what allows for the
variational bayesian inference which is
like doing bayesian model fitting
on a factorized
because it's sparsely connected graph
and so a lot of these discussions are
quite
downstream
of a lot of the philosophy of map and
territory but it's still super important
conversation
however within the model
inference with a model inference using a
model
a lot of these questions are are very
technical
and downstream
of importance
qualitative things that are also
important to keep in mind
but of a different type
jessica or anyone else
yeah wow very interesting
here's one other question i guess we can
discuss like
as the as it currently stands there's a
one hour meeting
and then at the end of the very next
hour begins
the dot tools regular organizational
unit meeting
so
is there i mean it is the people who are
here now but hopefully others would be
listening to it if they're not able to
make this time but like
what will help people with the
synchronous and asynchronous
make the most of the next few months
do people appreciate having a longer
discussion
for this
do people think that the
main versus the math group like is there
another subgroup like a philosophy
discussion that people want to like kind
of
really
do this
because we're not like
we don't we're experimenting with
open-endedness on our first cohort and
in these early phases of the book
and people can probably imagine various
of like the things we want to balance
like respecting everyone's time
and different backgrounds respecting
their preferences for
how much they want to learn about
different topics
being realistic about how much
asynchronous and synchronous
direct and peripheral
time makes sense
but also being realistic like
there isn't a two-minute video for a
process
so how do people think about like that
those who have stayed
this far
mike and then anyone else
can you hear me yes
okay
um
yeah i think that
as noted earlier in the discussion there
are just so many themes that run through
this
um that there are opportunities to
pull on any of a number of threads in
the course of discussion and so
uh today's discussion was interesting
and i stayed
for this part of this the discussion um
simply because of the interesting
threads that were being pulled
certainly a contrast with the first part
of the discussion around math and i
think a lot of uncertainty
amongst the attendees about
how to engage with the mathematical
aspects and so
maybe to try and put a point on it
um
from my perspective
learning about uh what is active
inference and how can active inference
be applied in real world situations
is a motivator for me participating
um
obviously there are also sort of
philosophical and maybe more scientific
discussions
that can take place and
so
any
any meeting could touch on any of those
aspects uh as well as some of the
asynchronous interaction could pick
those up as well
thanks a lot
okay anyone can raise their hand here's
just a few other
options like if somebody here's
something that's interesting to them we
can
in the discord
make a channel
that is relate or people can participate
in the regular channels just like
questions like or and that's going to
potentially be
seen and interacted with by people more
broadly like what if we posted questions
that we're having
we're in the cohort one of the texts we
you know had this question
do you know
that's one option another
um and this is like to mike's um
expression that applied active inference
is a
motivator
epistemic and pragmatic value
expected epistemic value we expect to
learn a lot by like staying in these
sometimes
challenging or oblique or whatever
discussions
but then there's also expected pragmatic
value
with applying active inference learning
and applying active inference
so then
maybe that is a group we can partition
like
an applied active inference group so
then
we can
be clear about what the focal artifact
is
because also we want to like
not
all groups at all times will be able to
have
uh nor is it useful to have open-ended
discussions of any discursion length
so like knowing how far and in what ways
and how many minutes of people's linear
time
um ali
yes
the edu meetings
um just one note on the organizational
unit meetings the organization units in
the active lab like edu
comms and tools for education
communication and tools
are like directory
one-hour
lab meetings
or group meetings because we're not
doing
the education work necessarily in that
one hour but some groups sometimes it's
possible to do some stuff
but it's like
increasingly moving towards
sharing updates
from people who want to commit in
asynchronous work or smaller groups that
want to commit to doing something like
that
so then
educational related projects that's
their opportunity to ask for help share
updates and so on
but
earlier on there was more topical
material
but then
through
particularization and operations
and other approaches
it becomes more like pragmatic and less
discovery and less mixed media role
specification all these processes so
people sticking around is sort of the
and being engaged and like seeing an
affordance and then just making that
contribution
wanting to be a facilitator for a
certain project or wanting to contribute
actively or just even connect with
another participant
like you can
email them if they've provided their
information
just some random things but like
we want to have the applied
angle the philosophical loop
and how to even partition that
discussion
like we couldn't just over go every math
every philosophy every applied question
and have
the judge and the jury
and all this apparatus
so
how can we scaffold that conversation
around applied active inference for the
people who are like super excited and
motivated mike
yeah i just want to add
there's an interesting duality related
to what you just said in that we can't
go into fine detail in all of the
content
um and at the same time i've found this
group
to be remarkable at unpacking things and
sort of
really getting into
what we mean when we say that uh types
of discussions and
uh what does this term mean not taking
things for your for granted
as going through the text and
so
there's a balance to be struck in taking
that approach of
asking what do we mean when we're
talking about this and putting nouns on
things and relating it to language
and not going too far over into getting
into fine detail about things
thank you lyle
and then i'll leave your question yeah
this bit this personally great session
really great conversation i really enjoy
it this is new much of this most of this
is new material for me and so
i'm really enjoying the breadth of the
conversation and i'm
cognizant of this uh
aspect you're digging into is you know
how much do we
sort of separate out the pieces and go
deep dive in different places versus
more of a
you know touching on multiple threads in
their interactions
uh
for me while i understand there is a
balance to be struck there i really
enjoying the
challenge of relating as an example the
math to the philosophy
to
all these different threads
together because they are linked right
and and so i do understand that you
can't
some of those
some of those areas
need a separate group that you can drill
down into for me personally and so this
may be not the same as other people in
the group i'm really enjoying
understanding the connections the
philosophy
how these different thought processes
came to be through history and get that
depth of understanding
thank you um lyle
and for those who want to like listen
or view
these live streams have many many themes
so check if there's papers that you're
interested in here
the live streams is about papers
so there's 46 papers
guest streams are not driven by a paper
sometimes the person's sharing a paper
but these are like presentations
hearing from different perspectives and
if anybody wants to
help organize these that's what we do in
comms if they want to facilitate and
participate in these discussions if they
want to like contact authors recommend
papers
these are all distributed tasks that
are leverage points for people who care
to just do a ton of amazing things like
if somebody's interested to connect it
to a given
community and make an artifact or live
stream co-organize that like
we can catalyze it at the lab scale for
individuals who know about the
affordance but then want to take that
affordance
to
just have really
leveraged impacts in the active
ecosystem so ali's question and then
jessica
sorry i don't have any questions
you asked about the timetable for the
edu
meetings
like what specific times are they
occurring at
sure yeah okay
they are on mondays at 13
and 23 utc
there's two edu meetings
to reflect like education being the
primary mission of actin flab and then
that spreads them out by time zones
but if somebody really wants to
contribute to an area
the organizational unit meeting is not
the rate limiting step
anyone who has attention to contribute
will be able to find a regime of
attention that is like connected to a
task that's meaningful the rate limiting
step is not people's availability for a
one hour meeting
it's however much time people want to
contribute whatever practices and things
will find something that works for
people who want to be engaged so don't
take these meeting times as being like
when we're doing it when we're deciding
even
anybody who wants to can email or
contact just the lab email address
and be started on figuring it that out
um jessica
um yes this was related to the question
about applied on projects um
i was thinking that maybe one thing that
we could do is um
on the project on ideas on cycling to
have a table and where people can like
you know briefly share what they want to
do or like you know use it say like okay
i'm interested in
machine learning and apply you know like
active inference and maybe this specific
topic
who will be interested in
discussing this or exploring what to do
and and then like adding the names of
the people who would be interested in
that and so the person who started the
you know seated the project then they
can be you know
can start like maybe contacting those
people and see like you know what time
they can meet and start like creating
their own sub groups um so maybe that's
something that we could do like to
facilitate that
and
in a simple way um
yeah so just start like saying like this
is what i would like to do apply active
inference while also studying the course
and you know i would like to connect
with people here who might share the
same interests and and you know see
what kind of feedback and
that person can get
thanks
and just
connecting and building trust
and having like a buddy system or small
groups or just people who are
on the relatively long path
to apply active inference on teams
we don't have the speed dating
hot swap
active application
protocol
but
connecting with people
and then
however it's authentic in that
relationship seeing what you're
interested in in three months
will be in a pretty different
situation
but we still won't have even gone
through
the second half of the book
on the application of the textbook
so there's a there's a lot of time for
us to
to develop ideas
and to connect with each other
so thanks for sharing that a lot jessica
and and i tagged you so that we can
create a table
with the right way or do it with however
is the right way
because it it helps enable connections
for people who want to
connect around applying
and also it helps us remember these are
the specific reference points in the
text
that
are like
our attractor regime of attention for
this
textbook group like the textbook group
isn't all of actin flap if people want
to apply active inference it doesn't
have to be
from the ground up but it totally could
be
but there's many ways to apply that are
just in different codas that people get
can get involved in immediately
so
if somebody feels like doing things
i hope they feel like they have the
agency to do that
okay any final thoughts on this
interesting
semi-pattern breaking
and also um
yes
one final thought for me is uh we would
have had dot tools organizational unit
meeting at this time
which is why near the end
like asked if you want to do different
scheduling
because
um
in general it's probably not good
practice or ways of working to like go
over time
to respect everyone's time and all of
these types of things
but also in the future we're in gather
so people who want to keep discussing
the textbook
could go there into a different room
people want to do tools can go into
another place
so we
need to figure out how to
do that through the people who want to
be there like these people and the
feedback that everybody has and the ways
they want to co-create it tim and then
anyone else who has like last thoughts
hey yeah i was just going to say this is
generally way more interesting than the
tools meeting generally is so
this is crossbow true
pollination shows great potential
already i would say um
yeah sounds good i just wanted to add to
that conversation though about uh
someone even mentioned plato socrates
and all that uh and that whole sort of
recursive involution of the of the sort
of uh that sort of
rarification thing you were talking
about and and sort of the the thought
processes maybe being almost like a
recapitulation of the of the that of the
structure learning and that and the
corrupt bayesian factor graphs and all
that kind of thing you were talking
about there um
plato had like a concept of knowledge
which which he referred to as
recollection
and and this idea way way back where all
all learning and knowledge is actually
an act of recollecting what we already
know
and i just want to point out there's
kind of a
maybe just more of a
interesting
uh
illusion or connection i guess between
those two whether it seems like a old
new what's what's old is new again or
what have you covered
thanks tim
anyone else who hasn't spoken or who
would like to add anything
okay